{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "2.2","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["Prolonged PT","Increased PLT aggregation","Thrombocytosis","Prolonged APTT"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Increased PLT aggregation","explanation": "TTP is a quantitative PLT disorder associated with increased intravascular PLT activation and aggregation resulting in thrombocytopenia. PT and APTT results are normal in TTP."},"question": "Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP) is characterized by:","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Platelets/2"},{"choices": ["Splenectomy","Hypersplenism","Acute blood loss","Increased proliferation of pluripotent stem cells"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Hypersplenism","explanation": "Hypersplenism is associated with thrombocytopenia. In this condition, up to 90% of PLTs can be sequestered in the spleen, causing decreases in circulatory PLTs. Splenectomy, acute blood loss, and increased proliferation of pluripotent stem cells are associated with thrombocytosis."},"question": "Thrombocytopenia may be associated with:","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Platelets/2"},{"choices": ["Phospholipase","Cyclo-oxygenase","Thromboxane A2 (TXA2) synthetase","Prostacyclin synthetase"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Cyclo-oxygenase","explanation": "Aspirin prevents PLT aggregation by inhibiting the activity of the enzyme cyclo- oxygenase. This inhibition prevents the formation of TXA2, which serves as a potent PLT aggregator."},"question": "Aspirin prevents PLT aggregation by inhibiting the action of which enzyme?","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Platelets/1"},{"choices": ["Fibrinogen","Glycoprotein Ib","Glycoprotein IIb–IIIa complex","Calcium"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Glycoprotein Ib","explanation": "Glycoprotein Ib is a PLT receptor for VWF. Glycoprotein Ib and VWF are both necessary for a normal PLT adhesion. Other proteins that play a role in PLT adhesion are glycoproteins V and IX."},"question": "Normal PLT adhesion depends on:","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Platelets/1"},{"choices": ["PLT aggregation","APTT","PLT count","Factor VIII:C and von Willebrand factor (VWF) levels"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "PLT count","explanation": "Von Willebrand disease is an inherited, qualitative PLT disorder that results in increased bleeding, prolonged APTT, and decreased factor VIII:C and VWF levels. The PLT count and morphology are generally normal in von Willebrand disease, but PLT aggregation in the PLT function assay is abnormal."},"question": "Which of the following test results is normal in a patient with classic von Willebrand disease?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Platelet disorders/2"},{"choices": ["Decreased factor IX","Decreased factor VIII","Thrombocytopenia and giant PLTs","Abnormal PLT function test results"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Thrombocytopenia and giant PLTs","explanation": "Bernard–Soulier syndrome is associated with thrombocytopenia and giant PLTs. It is a qualitative PLT disorder caused by the deficiency of glycoprotein Ib. In Bernard– Soulier syndrome, PLT aggregation in the PLT function assay is abnormal. Factor VIII and IX assays are not indicated for this diagnosis."},"question": "Bernard–Soulier syndrome is associated with:","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Platelet disorders/2"},{"choices": ["Normal PLT aggregation to collagen, adenosine diphosphate (ADP), and ristocetin","Normal PLT aggregation to collagen, ADP, and epinephrine (EPI); decreased aggregation to ristocetin","Normal PLT aggregation to EPI and ristocetin; decreased aggregation to collagen and ADP","Normal PLT aggregation to EPI, ristocetin, and collagen; decreased aggregation to ADP"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Normal PLT aggregation to collagen, ADP, and epinephrine (EPI); decreased aggregation to ristocetin","explanation": "Bernard–Soulier syndrome is a disorder of PLT adhesion caused by deficiency of glycoprotein Ib. PLT aggregation is normal in response to collagen, ADP, and EPI but abnormal in response to ristocetin."},"question": "When performing PLT aggregation studies, which set of PLT aggregation results would most likely be associated with Bernard–Soulier syndrome?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Platelet disorders/2"},{"choices": ["Normal PLT aggregation to ADP and ristocetin; decreased aggregation to collagen","Normal PLT aggregation to collagen; decreased aggregation to ADP and ristocetin","Normal PLT aggregation to ristocetin; decreased aggregation to collagen, ADP, and EPI","Normal PLT aggregation to ADP; decreased aggregation to collagen and ristocetin"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Normal PLT aggregation to ristocetin; decreased aggregation to collagen, ADP, and EPI","explanation": "Glanzmann thrombasthenia is a disorder of PLT aggregation. PLT aggregation is normal in response to ristocetin, but abnormal in response to collagen, ADP, and EPI."},"question": "Which set of PLT responses would be most likely associated with Glanzmann thrombasthenia?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Platelet disorders/2"},{"choices": ["Spontaneous remission within a few weeks","Predominantly seen in adults","Nonimmune PLT destruction","Insidious onset"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Spontaneous remission within a few weeks","explanation": "Acute immune thrombocytopenic purpura is an immune-mediated disorder found predominantly in children. It is commonly associated with infection (primarily viral). It is characterized by abrupt onset, and spontaneous remission usually occurs within several weeks."},"question": "Which of the following is a characteristic of acute immune thrombocytopenic purpura?","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Platelet disorders/2"},{"choices": ["APTT is normal in TTP but prolonged in DIC","Schistocytes are not present in TTP but are present in DIC","PLT count is decreased in TTP but normal in DIC","PT is prolonged in TTP but decreased in DIC"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "APTT is normal in TTP but prolonged in DIC","explanation": "TTP is a PLT disorder in which PLT aggregation increases, resulting in thrombocytopenia. Schistocytes are present in TTP as a result of microangiopathic hemolytic anemia (MAHA); however, the PT and APTT are both normal. In DIC, the PT and APTT are both prolonged, the PLT count is decreased, and schistocytes are seen in the peripheral blood smear."},"question": "TTP differs from DIC in that:","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Platelet disorders/2"},{"choices": ["Drug-induced thrombocytopenia","Secondary thrombocytopenia","Neonatal alloimmune thrombocytopenia","Neonatal DIC"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Neonatal alloimmune thrombocytopenia","explanation": "Neonatal alloimmune thrombocytopenia is similar to the hemolytic disease of the fetus and newborn. It results from immunization of the mother by fetal PLT antigens. The offending antibodies are commonly anti-PLT antigen A1 (PlA1), also referred to as human platelet antigen (HPA) 1a. These alloantibodies are directed against glycoproteins IIb/IIIa, Ib/IX, Ia/IIb, and CD 109. Maternal antibodies cross the placenta, resulting in thrombocytopenia in the fetus."},"question": "Several hours after birth, a baby boy develops petechiae and purpura and hemorrhagic diathesis. The PLT count is 18 × 109/L. What is the most likely explanation for the low PLT count?","reference": "Hemostasis/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Platelet disorders/3"},{"choices": ["Nonimmune thrombocytopenia/alloantibodies","Immune-mediated thrombocytopenia/alloantibodies","Immune-mediated thrombocytopenia/autoantibodies","Nonimmune-mediated thrombocytopenia/autoantibodies"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Immune-mediated thrombocytopenia/alloantibodies","explanation": "PTP is a rare form of alloimmune thrombocytopenia characterized by severe thrombocytopenia occurring after transfusion of blood or blood products. PTP is caused by antibody-related PLT destruction in previously immunized patients. In the majority of cases, the alloantibody produced is against PlA1 (HPA-1a)."},"question": "Which of the following is associated with post-transfusion purpura (PTP)?","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Platelet disorders/2"},{"choices": ["Fever, thrombocytosis, anemia, and renal failure","Fever, granulocytosis, and thrombocytosis","Escherichia coli 0157:H7","Leukocytosis and thrombocytosis"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Escherichia coli 0157:H7","explanation": "HUS is caused by E. coli 0157:H7. It is associated with ingestion of E. coli– contaminated foods and is commonly seen in children. The clinical manifestations in HUS are fever, diarrhea, thrombocytopenia, MAHA, and renal failure."},"question": "Hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS) is associated with:","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Platelet disorders/2"},{"choices": ["PLT adhesion","PLT aggregation","PLT granules","PLT production"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "PLT granules","explanation": "Storage pool deficiencies are defects of PLT granules. Most commonly, a decrease in PLT-dense granules is present with decreased release of ADP, ATP, calcium, and serotonin from PLT-dense granules."},"question": "Storage pool deficiencies are defects of:","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Platelet disorders/1"},{"choices": ["PLT aggregation only","PLT aggregation and adenosine triphosphate (ATP) release","PLT adhesion","PLT glycoprotein Ib"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "PLT aggregation and adenosine triphosphate (ATP) release","explanation": "Lumi-aggregation measures PLT aggregation and ATP release. It is performed on whole blood diluted with saline. PLT aggregation is measured by impedance, whereas ATP release is measured by addition of luciferin to a blood sample. There is no ATP release in storage pool deficiencies."},"question": "Lumi-aggregation measures:","reference": "Hemostasis/Select methods/Reagents/Specimen collection and handling/Aggregometry/1"},{"choices": ["HUS", "TTP", "ITP", "PTP"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "TTP","explanation": "TTP is characterized by neurological problems, fever, thrombocytopenia, MAHA, and renal failure."},"question": "Neurological findings may be commonly associated with which of the following disorders?","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Platelet function/1"},{"choices": ["Autoimmune disease","Decreased VWF","Decreased PLT aggregation","Decreased PLT adhesion"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Autoimmune disease","explanation": "Acquired TTP is an autoimmune disease associated with autoantibodies produced against VWF cleaving enzyme (ADAMTS-13). This deficiency results in an increase in plasma VWF and consequently increased PLT aggregation and thrombocytopenia."},"question": "Which of the following is correct regarding acquired TTP?","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Platelet disorders/2"},{"choices": ["PLTs","Clotting proteins","Fibrinolysis","Connective tissue"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Connective tissue","explanation": "Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia (Osler–Weber–Rendu syndrome) is a connective tissue disorder associated with telangiectases (dilated capillaries) of the mucous membranes and skin. Lesions may develop on the tongue, lips, palate, face, hands, and nasal mucosa and throughout the gastrointestinal tract. This disorder is an autosomal dominant condition that usually manifests in adolescence or early adulthood."},"question": "Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia is a disorder of:","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/2"},{"choices": ["TXA2","Thromboxane B2","Prostacyclin","Antithrombin (AT)"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Prostacyclin","explanation": "Prostacyclin is released from the endothelium and is an inhibitor of PLT aggregation. TXA2 promotes PLT aggregation. Thromboxane B2 is an oxidized form of TXA2 and is excreted in urine. AT is a physiological anticoagulant."},"question": "Which of the following prevents PLT aggregation?","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Platelets/2"},{"choices": ["PLT adhesion defect","Dense granule defect","Alpha granule defect","Coagulation defect"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Alpha granule defect","explanation": "Gray syndrome is a PLT granule defect associated with a decrease in alpha granules resulting in decreased production of alpha granule proteins, such as PF4 and beta thromboglobulin. Alpha granule deficiency results in the appearance of agranular PLTs when viewed in a Wright-stained blood smear."},"question": "Which defect characterizes Gray syndrome?","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Platelet disorders/2"},{"choices": ["Warfarin","Heparin","Low-molecular-weight heparin (LMWH)","Clopidogrel (Plavix)"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Clopidogrel (Plavix)","explanation": "The VerifyNow P2Y12 test is used to assess a patient’s response to antiplatelet drugs, such as clopidogrel (Plavix) and prasugrel (Effient). These drugs are given orally along with aspirin for prevention of thrombosis or as alternative antiplatelet drugs for patients who cannot tolerate or are not sensitive to aspirin. Clopidogrel and prasugrel prevent PLT aggregation by irreversibly binding to P2Y12, which is a PLT membrane receptor for ADP. The VerifyNow P2Y12 test is a whole blood test and uses ADP as an aggregating agent to measure the level of PLT aggregation impaired by these medications. The baseline value for PLT aggregation is established. The percent (%) change from baseline aggregation is calculated and reported as % P2Y12 inhibition."},"question": "The P2Y12 ADP receptor agonist assay may be used to monitor PLT aggregation inhibition to which of the following drugs?","reference": "Hemostasis/Selected methods/Reagents/Special tests/2"},{"choices": ["PLT aggregometer","VerifyNow","PFA-100","All of the above"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "All of the above","explanation": "All of the instruments listed can be used to evaluate PLT function. PLT function testing is done either to determine the cause of bleeding in a patient with normal PLT count and normal coagulation tests or to assess the efficacy of antiplatelet drugs. PLT aggregometry is used for the diagnosis of inherited PLT disorders. A PLT aggregometer uses PLT-rich plasma to measure PLT aggregation in response to different PLT aggregating agents by measuring light transmission. A Lumi-aggregometer uses whole blood and has the ability to measure dense-granule secretion (by using a luminescent marker) in addition to PLT aggregation. The VerifyNow measures a patient’s response to multiple antiplatelet drugs, including aspirin, P2Y12 inhibitors, and glycoprotein IIb/IIIa inhibitors. The Platelet Function Ananlyzer-100 (PFA-100) is used as a screening tool for PLT function, and has replaced the bleeding time test. It uses citrated whole blood and two cartridges. Whole blood (800 μL) is put into each test cartridge. Vacuum is used to move the blood through a very thin glass tube that has been coated with a membrane containing collagen and either EPI or ADP. This coating activates the PLTs in the moving sample and promotes PLT adhesion and aggregation. The time it takes for the clot to form inside the glass tube and prevent further flow is measured as the closure time (CT). Initial screening is done with collagen/EPI. If CT is normal, it is unlikely that PLT dysfunction exists. The collagen/ADP membrane is used to confirm an abnormal collagen/EPI test result. If both tests show abnormal results, it is likely that the patient has a PLT dysfunction, and further testing for inherited and acquired bleeding disorders is indicated. If collagen/ADP is normal, then the abnormal collagen/EPI test result is likely caused by aspirin sensitivity."},"question": "Which of the following instruments can be used to evaluate PLT function?","reference": "Hemostasis/Selected methods/Reagents/Special tests/2"},{"choices": ["Thrombin", "Collagen", "ADP", "EPI"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Collagen","explanation": "Collagen is the only commonly used agent that demonstrates a single-wave (monophasic) response preceded by a lag time."},"question": "Which of the following PLT aggregating agents demonstrates a monophasic aggregation curve when used in the optimal concentration?","reference": "Hemostasis/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Aggregating agents/1"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Platelet and Vascular Disorders"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}